Guide to the Irish-American Labor Coalition Records AIA.094
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish-American Labor Coalition Records
1978-2014
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish-American Labor Council
Jamison, Joe
AIA.094
2.92 Linear Feet in 7 manuscript boxes
3 VHS
The Irish-American Labor Council (IALC) was a New York City area organization that resolved to effect material solidarity with the Irish Republican movement in the late 20th-century. As part of their engagement with the peace process in Northern Ireland, the IALC activated local state labor councils around adopting the MacBride Principles, nine fair employment principles for US corporations operating in Northern Ireland. Public sector pension funds were required by state legislation to invest only in companies that abided by the Principles. The organization also revived commemorations of James Connolly, including building several statues of Connolly and creating a banner that was carried in the St. Patrick's Day and Labor Day parade. Similarly, the organization was involved in the restoration of Matilda Tone's grave in Green-wood Cemetery. The Irish-American Labor Coalition was also influential in bringing Gerry Adams to the United States, holding President Bill Clinton accountable to his promise to clear Adams' visa for travel. The Irish-American Labor Coalition Records (dated 1978-2014) consists of memoranda, newsletters, reports, clippings, correspondence, photographs, meeting agendas, pamphlets and other publications, Sinn Féin discussion papers, solidarity statements and press releases, and by-laws and incorporation documents. The collection also documents some of the organization's notable achievements, including the administrative efforts to secure Gerry Adams' visit to the United States, encouraging state labor councils to adopt the MacBride Principles, and reviving commemorations of James Connolly and Matilda Tone.
Scope and Contents
The Irish-American Labor Coalition Records (dated 1978-2014) consists of materials created and collected by the IALC in their efforts to pursue more concrete solidarity with the Irish Republican movement. Materials include memoranda, newsletters, reports, clippings, correspondence, photographs, meeting agendas, pamphlets and other publications, Sinn Féin discussion papers, solidarity statements and press releases, and by-laws and incorporation documents. The collection also documents some of the organization's notable achievements, including the administrative efforts to secure Gerry Adams' visit to the United States, encouraging state labor councils to adopt the MacBride Principles, and reviving commemorations of James Connolly and Matilda Tone. Also included are three video recordings of parades and a speech by John Sweeney to the Irish Trade Union Congress. The collection documents the broader context of Irish American engagement with the peace process in Northern Ireland, including the administrative efforts undertaken by smaller organizations that impacted more visible diplomatic interventions.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joe Jamison in April 2025; the accession number associated with this gift is 2025.054.
Appraisal
Financial records and one duplicate VHS recording were appraised out of the collection prior to acquisition.
Historical Note
The Irish-American Labor Council (IALC) was a New York City area organization that resolved to effect material solidarity with the Irish Republican movement in the late 20th-century. John Sweeney from Service Employees International Union (SEIU), John Lawe from Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), William Treacy from the Operating Engineers, and Dan Kane from the Teamsters in particular, were concerned with forming an organization to advance the cause of Irish freedom and unity by enlisting the support of American trade unionists. Joe Jamison had been working as an economist and had a background working with civil rights organizations in Northern Ireland. He was brought onto the newly formed IALC to develop a program of activity. As part of these efforts, the Irish-American Labor Coalition activated local state labor councils around adopting the MacBride Principles, nine fair employment principles for US corporations operating in Northern Ireland. Public sector pension funds were required by state legislation to invest only in companies that abided by the Principles. The organization also revived commemorations of James Connolly, including building several statues of Connolly and creating a banner that was carried in the St. Patrick's Day and Labor Day parade. Similarly, the organization was involved in the restoration of Matilda Tone's grave in Green-wood Cemetery. The Irish-American Labor Coalition was also influential in bringing Gerry Adams to the United States, holding President Bill Clinton accountable to his promise to clear Adams' visa for travel. Adams later cited the importance of the visit and the granting of the visa to the peace process.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Northern Ireland -- History -- 1968-1998; Human rights -- Northern Ireland.; Peace movements -- Northern Ireland; Labor movement -- United States.; MacBride Principles.; Jamison, Joe; Adams, Gerry, 1948-; Connolly, James, 1868-1916; Sinn Fein
- Chronological Files -- 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Chronological Files -- 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Chronological Files -- 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
- Chronological Files -- 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Chronological Files -- 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12, Box 2, Folder 1)
- Chronological Files -- 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
- Chronological Files -- 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Chronological Files -- 1988 -- MacBride Principles (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chronological Files -- 1989 -- John Lawe (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Chronological Files -- 1992 -- Clippings and Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Chronological Files -- 1993 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Chronological Files -- 1994 (Box 2, Folder 10-11, Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- Chronological Files -- 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4-10)
- Chronological Files -- 1996 (Box 3, Folder 11, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
- Chronological Files -- 1997 -- Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Chronological Files -- 1998 -- Peace Process (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Chronological Files -- 1999 -- American Conference for Irish Studies (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Chronological Files -- 2013-2014 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Incorporation, By-laws, 1987-1999 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Pamphlets, 1978-1995 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
- Publications, 1984-1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- "Policing: A New Beginning? The Pattern Recommendations: A Benchmark for the British Government's Legislation and Implementation Plan (A Comparative Study)," Report by Sinn Féin Sub-Committee on Policing, circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- James Larkin Memorial, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 13-17, Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Gerry Adams Visit to United States -- General, 1993-1997 (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
- Gerry Adams Visit to United States -- Conference on Northern Ireland, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Matilda Tone, 1990-1998 (Box 5, Folder 7-11)
- Unions, 1983-2012 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
- MacBride Principles, 1978-2002 (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
- Jimmy Gralton, 1982-1986 (Box 6, Folder 10, Box 7, Folder 1)
- Clippings, Correspondence, and Ephemera, 1983-2012 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
- Charter for Change, 1996-1998 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
- Correspondence -- James Connolly Banner for Transport Workers Union of America (TWU), undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Video Recording -- 100th Anniversary of the Irish Trade Unions and May Day Parade, Dublin, May 2, 1994; cuid44255 (Box Shared Tamiment 201, Vhs cuid44255)
- Video Recording -- AFL-CIO President John J. Sweeney Address to the Irish Trade Union Congress, June 1997; cuid44256 (Box Shared Tamiment 201, Vhs cuid44256)
- Video Recording -- May Day Parade, Dublin, undated; cuid44257 (Box Shared Tamiment 201, Vhs cuid44257)